Captions for PyGotham TV 2021 are sponsored by Two Sigma
- Hello, PyGotham.
My name is Simon, and
I'm going to show you
in just 10 minutes, how to build,
test and publish an open
source Python library.
I'm actually going to publish
a library while I record this talk.
This is a piece of code,
which I've been copying
and pasting into projects
for over a decade now.
It's a very simple little thing
that helps you create string based
shortened versions of numeric identifiers.
I'll do a quick demonstration
of what that looks like.
Let's paste it into a Jupyter notebook.
And now if I do pid.from_int (1234),
it says, gxd.
And if I do pid.to_int
of gxd, it says 1234.
So very simple piece of code.
Let's turn this into a package
on the Python package on
the Python package index.
So I'm going to create
a directory called pids.
I checked, and this is an
available name right now.
And I'm going to add that file.
Let's create a new file called pid.py.
We'll stick it in that folder
and we'll paste in that code.
So that's my code.
Creating a package, all you need for sure
is a setup.py file,
which describes how the package will work.
So I'm going to create that.
And then I'm going to paste
in this little template here.
This is the simplest possible version
of a valid set up .py file.
I'm going to give it the
name, pids, version 0.1.,
it's a tiny Python library
in the description.
And the only module
I'm going to include is
that pids.py file I just created.
So now in here we have two files, pid.py,
and setup.py.
Now, if I run python3 setup.py sdist,
this is where the magic happens,
that command back created me
a file called pids-0.1.tar.gz.
And that is a file,
which I can install into any environment
to install this package.
Can actually demonstrate that once again,
in this Jupyter notebook,
let's pop that open and
we'll do pip install,
paste that, what was it
/dist/, pids, there we go.
When that processes it, it installs it.
And now if I type import pids,
I have pids.pid as a piece of code
that I can start to run.
So let's upload this to the
Python the package index,
where we do that is with
a tool called twine.
I can say twine upload
dist and then pasted
the name of that file
that I've just created.
When I do this, it'll ask me to log in
with my username and my PyPI password.
So you'll need to create an account
on PyPI before you do this.
I do that.
It shows me the upload
and it gives me a URL.
And this is live on
the internet right now.
This is now a package which anyone
in the world can install by
running pip install pids.
But you'll notice it says here,
the author of this package
has not provided a project description.
We're missing our documentation.
So let's build that
now as a simple read me
that we can add into that package.
So here's a tiny bit of
documentation I wrote earlier.
I'm going to save that in
a file called README.md
and VS Code can give us a little preview
of it, showing you what that looks like.
Not very exciting,
but it does explain what's going on.
So now we need to bundle
that into our overall package and
the why we do that is by adding
a tiny bit more of a recipe
to our setup.py file.
Here we go. I'll copy and paste this in.
So we can add two more arguments here.
There's description, long description
and long description, content type.
And here we're doing,
we're calling a function I've written
called get long description,
which reads that weekly file on disc
and puts that in a variable.
So we add this a little
bit of boiler plate,
and we set that as the long description,
I'm going to bump up the
version number to 0.1.1,
to reflect that change.
And now once again,
we can run python3 setup.py sdist.
Oh, it doesn't like that 'cause
I forgot the input OS there.
Could do that.
We now have a file in
dist called pids-0.1.1,
and again, if we do twine
upload dist/pids-0.1.1.
And stick in those
credentials one more time.
This has given us our
second release on PyPI
and this release, it's improved.
It's got documentation.
The contents of that readme
is now available for people to see.
So for our next step,
let's add some tests.
I'm going to need a tiny bit
more boiler plate for this.
I need to add pytest as a test dependency.
So I'll paste this in here.
This is saying that the
pids test dependencies
are pytest, and now I'm
going to create myself
a Python virtual environment.
I'll call it venv.
I'll do source venv/bin/activate
to activate it.
And I'm going to type pip installe -e,
editable of my current directory
and it's test dependencies.
So running this installs pytest.
Now, if I run pytest, it runs my test,
except I don't have any tests yet.
So let's create a test folder,
and I'm going to create a file
in that called test_pids.py.
And the great thing about pytest is
that tests are really,
really small, short.
So let's say a test_from_int():
and it's going to say
assert pids.pid.from_int(1234)=="mzq"
So I'll try running that test.
And it fails because I
got it wrong it's gxd
is the correct value.
So I can stick gxd in
and now my test passes.
I'll do that in the opposite direction.
So I'll test test_to_int("gsd") == 1234
And when that tests there,
1235, gxf, gxd that's why.
And so now I have a passing test suite,
and this can obviously
be extended to be a lot more thorough.
So the next step is to
get this up on, github.
I'm going to create a new
GitHub repo called pids.
I'll use the default settings for that.
And then handy thing about GitHub
is it just gives you the commands
you need to run for you
to copy and paste in.
So I'll do that.
I'm going to git add my README,
my pids.py, my setup.py,
and that test as well.
And then I'll paste in
these four lines here,
and that will go ahead
and create that repository for me.
But the really neat thing about GitHub
these days is you can use GitHub
actions to run your tests for you.
The way you do that is be by creating
a Github workflows directory.
So rather than create that by hand,
I'm going to copy that
from a project I worked on recently,
My sqlite explain project
I happen to know has one of these.
And I'm gonna copy that folder here.
So now, if we look in here,
we now have a GitHub folder
with a publish.yml and a test.yml.
This right here is the one
we're going to try out first.
What this does is it installs the package
under four different versions of Python,
loads that and runs those tests for us.
So I can now do git add.github
git commit, GitHub Actions, git push.
And over here, GitHub will spot that
those actions have been
configured and start running
that test action for me straight away.
You can see that this actually
turns into four different
jobs and GitHub actions.
One for each of those versions of Python
that we are targeting,
and it's already started running those.
It's running them in parallel,
all different four version.
We look at this one here,
it's set up some caching
it's installed dependencies.
It's run the tests and they've passed
and we can see the
green ticks clicking in.
And just like that, our test has been run
on four versions of Python and our
comment there even gets
a little green tick
to show what had happened.
So I have one last trick up my sleeve.
I'm going to push a new release directly
from GitHub and without running anything
on my computer at all.
Where I'm going to do this is by creating
a API token on PyPI called pids.
I'm gonna give it this scope
of being able to publish
to that pids project
and that token,
and I will copy this token and then paste
it into the Secrets for
my GitHub repository.
So I can do, add secret,
call it PYPI token and paste it in here.
And now anytime I push a release
to this GitHub repository,
my published work flow
will run more published that release.
So I'm gonna modify my version number.
Let's call this 0.1.2,
And I'm going to publish a new release.
It's create new release.
It's going to be called 0.1.2.
And let's just say,
Added tests, full stop.
I hit the publish button.
And once again, that
action kicks into effect.
So this is my published
Python package action,
which is running the tests first,
because you wouldn't want
to publish your package if you
haven't thoroughly tested it.
And once the tests are passed
hit deploy action,
which ones that coin upload scripts
that I showed you earlier.
So this right here is installing
the required packages.
And now it's publishing
that package up to PyPI,
that's done. And here is a package
on PyPI that was published entirely
through automation using GitHub actions.
So thanks for listening,
and I've published extensive notes on at
github.com/simonw/pygotham-packaging.